<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sst uniqueCount="126" xmlns="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/spreadsheetml/2006/main"><si><t>This document was exported from Numbers.  Each table was converted to an Excel worksheet. All other objects on each Numbers sheet were placed on separate worksheets. Please be aware that formula calculations may differ in Excel.</t></si><si><t>Numbers Sheet Name</t></si><si><t>Numbers Table Name</t></si><si><t>Excel Worksheet Name</t></si><si><t>Summary Risk Assessment</t></si><si><t>Table 1</t></si><si><t>RESPONSIBLE AI STARTUPS (RAIS) Framework</t></si><si><t xml:space="preserve">Radical Ventures, 2023 </t></si><si><t>Initial Risk</t></si><si><t>(Max)</t></si><si><t>Remaining Risk</t></si><si><t>Social and Ethical</t></si><si><t>Industry-Specific and Regulatory</t></si><si><t>IS and Regulatory</t></si><si><t>Technical</t></si><si><t>Likelihood:</t></si><si><t>Very likely</t></si><si><t>Likely</t></si><si><t>Somewhat likely</t></si><si><t>Neither unlikely nor likely</t></si><si><t>Somewhat unlikely</t></si><si><t>Unlikely</t></si><si><t>Very unlikely</t></si><si><t>Impact:</t></si><si><t>Very insignificant impact</t></si><si><t>Insignificant impact</t></si><si><t>Somewhat insignificant impact</t></si><si><t>Neither insignificant nor significant</t></si><si><t>Somewhat significant impact</t></si><si><t>Significant impact</t></si><si><t>Very significant impact</t></si><si><t>Risk Levels</t></si><si><t>Risk 1-10</t></si><si><t>Low Risk</t></si><si><t>Risk 11-20</t></si><si><t>Some Risk</t></si><si><t>Risk 21-30</t></si><si><t>Medium Risk</t></si><si><t>Risk 31-40</t></si><si><t>High Risk</t></si><si><t>Risk 41-50</t></si><si><t>Severe Risk</t></si><si><t>Risk Assessment: Social and Ethical</t></si><si><t>Vulnerability / Threat</t></si><si><t>Details</t></si><si><t>Likelihood</t></si><si><t>Impact</t></si><si><t>Mitigating Measures/Requirements for Uses (if any)</t></si><si><t>Date of Last Update</t></si><si><t>Restricted Uses</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Uses of the system that are subject to a legal restriction, list them here and the likelihood that the system would not meet requirements.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">- Robot could be used outside of a secure environment
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Robot could be asked to perform tasks that endanger humans</t></r></si><si><t>Ensure there is a failsafe that overrides unsafe instructions. Be mindful of who you are selling your product to (e.g., defense and army contractors)</t></si><si><t>Unsupported Uses</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Potential uses for which the system was not designed or evaluated or that should be avoided, list them here and the likelihood that this usecase would occur.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Robot could be used to perform new tasks not covered in its original training with unexpected consequences</t></r></si><si><t>Train the model on edgecases. Implement a failsafe where the system shuts down if it is going to harm someone or some thing, regardless of it that is part of its ask.</t></si><si><t>Sensitive Uses – Consequential impact on legal position or life opportunities</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Scenarios where the use or misuse of the AI system could affect an individual’s: legal status, legal rights, access to credit, education, employment, healthcare, housing, insurance, and social welfare benefits, services, or opportunities, or the terms on which they are provided.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Improper use can result in harm to humans, animals or property</t></r></si><si><t>This is where a failsafe mechanism would be useful.</t></si><si><t>Sensitive Uses – Risk of physical or psychological injury</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Scenarios where the use or misuse of the AI system could result in significant physical or psychological injury to an individual.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Improper use can result in harm to humans</t></r></si><si><t>This is where a failsafe mechanism would be useful, where it is hard-coded in the system that any ask that requires directly or indirectlty harming humans or animals, should be ignored.</t></si><si><t>Threat to Human Rights</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Scenarios where the use or misuse of the AI system could restrict, infringe upon, or undermine the ability to realize an individual’s human rights. (Note: because human rights are interdependent and interrelated, AI can affect nearly every internationally recognized human right.)
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Robot could be used as a guard to prevent humans from escaping</t></r></si><si><t>Known Limitations</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe the known limitations of the system. This could include scenarios where the system will not perform well, environmental factors to consider, or other operating factors to be aware of.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Actual limitations will depend on specific sensors and training of the robot, but risks are generally related to operating outside of the functional range of its sensors, in environments that the robot has not be trained for and to perform tasks that can't be properly generalized from the training received by the robot</t></r></si><si><t>Create a system that is as generalizable as possible. Obtain training data in a variety of different scenarios, weather conditions, times of year, and with different sensors.</t></si><si><t>Relationships – Supply chain, customers, and partnerships</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe vulnerabilities associated with the company's relationships including  supply chain, customers, vendors, and strategic partnerships. 
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Creating a physical robot that is good replica of its digital twin (requried if we assume learning will take place in a virtual space) is a complex and costly task, often requiring global supply chains which may be exposed to social &amp; ethical risks.</t></r></si><si><t>Ensure the sensitive information is encrypted when stored, and ensure cloud security. Ensure that any partners or contractors we work with adhere to the same ethical and social guidelines as we do.</t></si><si><t>Management</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe vulnerabilities associated with the company's management team including track record, diversity in skillsets, as well as considerations for diversity, equity, and inclusion, and codifying  decision-making processes.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- No data</t></r></si><si><t>N/A</t></si><si><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Max </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>Initial</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> risk</t></r></si><si><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Max </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>Remaining</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> risk</t></r></si><si><t>Negligible</t></si><si><t>Managed by routine mitigation; covered in normal procedures</t></si><si><t>Requires specific mitigation and caution</t></si><si><t>Immediate action required</t></si><si><t>Unacceptable</t></si><si><t>Impact Significance</t></si><si><t>0</t></si><si><t>1-2</t></si><si><t>No or insignificant risk to assets and personnel, and/or low negative impact on stakeholders or company</t></si><si><t>3-4</t></si><si><t>Somewhat insignificant risk to assets and personnel, and/or some negative impact on stakeholders or company</t></si><si><t>5-6</t></si><si><t>Meaningful risk to assets and personnel, and/or negative impact on stakeholders or company</t></si><si><t>Life threatening risk and/or critical negative impact on stakeholders or company</t></si><si><t>Industry-Specific and Regulator</t></si><si><t>Risk Assessment: Industry-Specific and Regulatory</t></si><si><t>Likelihood (of non-compliance)</t></si><si><t>Impact (if non-compliant)</t></si><si><t>Impact (of non-compliance)</t></si><si><t>Industry-specific considerations</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe any industry-specific regulatory  considerations where the AI technology is being applied and consider the company's capacity for compliance with industry-specific regulations, e.g. HIPAA. 
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- None known</t></r></si><si><t>Regulatory considerations</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe regulatory requirements for the operating jurisdiction and consider the company's capacity for compliance.
</t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">
</t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">This may include compliance with data protection and privacy regulations, such as GDPR and CCPA;  liability and accountability for AI decisions and actions; intellectual property, including copyright and patent infringement risks.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">- Regulation is limited to Safety in the Workplace regulation
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Insurance may introduce additional restrictions</t></r></si><si><t>Ensure employees have access to programs for Safety in Workplace awareness.</t></si><si><t>Meets requirements; managed by routine mitigation; covered in normal procedures</t></si><si><t>May meet requirements; requires specific mitigation and caution</t></si><si><t>Unlikely to meet requirements; immediate action required</t></si><si><t>Does not meet requirements; unacceptable</t></si><si><t>No or insignificant risk to assets and personnel, and/or low negative impact on company</t></si><si><t>Somewhat insignificant risk to assets and personnel, and/or some negative impact on company</t></si><si><t>Meaningful risk to assets and personnel, and/or negative impact on company</t></si><si><t>Life threatening risk and/or critical negative impact on company</t></si><si><t>Risk Assessment: Data</t></si><si><t>Data requirements</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe risks associated with the data requirements with respect to the system’s intended uses, stakeholders, and the geographic areas where the system will be deployed. (Note: omit regulatory consideration and include on the &quot;Industry-Specific and Regulatory&quot; tab.)
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">- Good-quality RL  environments for training the robot are available
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- CV model in a construction environment is still risky as there is a lot of variability depending on cluttering, wheather, standard safety practices, signaling, etc.</t></r></si><si><t>Must follow recognized safety practices when collecting data in a warehouse/construction zone. Must look into CV models for semi-static and dynamic environments.</t></si><si><t>Models &amp; infrastructure – Technology readiness</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>Describe  technology readiness –  the likelihood  the system is</t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> not </t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">supported by research and has </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>not</t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> been deployed to production systems at scale for similar uses and the associated impact on users and stakeholders.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Similar models have been implemented, but generally in narrower domains and/or controlled environments</t></r></si><si><t>Perform research and literature review on what models are out there for such environments.</t></si><si><t>Models &amp; infrastructure – Task complexity</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe the task complexity – the likelihood that there will be a </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>high number of features</t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> as well as</t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> difficult interpretability</t></r><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> and complexity in setting boundaries for classification categories, etc. and the associated impact on users and stakeholders.
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">- There is compounded challenges here with at least 2 sophisticated systems providing feedback into each other. </t></r></si><si><t>A thorough review on what has already been achieved, should be performed, in order to build on such existing robotics and CV frameworks.</t></si><si><t xml:space="preserve">Models &amp; infrastructure –  Energy and environmental considerations </t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe the likelihood for large energy consumption and other considerations focused on environmental impacts linked to model training and inference and the associated impact at large. 
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- Unlikely to be a primary concern as the model is expected to be trained centrally.</t></r></si><si><t>Carbon footprints and emissions are important to consider when incoporating new features in the model.</t></si><si><t xml:space="preserve">Models &amp; infrastructure –  Auditability and community </t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe any additional potential risks pertaining to specifically to  third party auditability of systems and models and community inclusion. 
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- These families of systems can be built with reasonable auditability and traceability.</t></r></si><si><t>Scope, scaling, &amp; maintenance</t></si><si><r><rPr><i val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Describe any risks or vulnerability associated with scaling, adapting, and maintaining the technology including existential risk as a product of scale and its impact at large. 
</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="19"/><rFont val="Calibri"/></rPr><t>- As the environment changes, the likelihood of dataset shift increases. This risk will depend on how controlled the environment is.</t></r></si><si><t>Scaling the systems may need re-train the models and it would impact the controlled environment.</t></si><si><r><rPr><b val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Max </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><u val="single"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t>Initial</t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> risk</t></r></si><si><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve">Average </t></r><r><rPr><b val="1"/><u val="single"/><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t>Remaining</t></r><r><rPr><sz val="11"/><color indexed="8"/><rFont val="Calibri, Arial"/></rPr><t xml:space="preserve"> risk</t></r></si></sst>
